Joel A. Masselink

Residing in: Seattle, Washington phone: +1 (774) 232-7629 website: www.joelmasselink.com e-mail: jmasselink@gmail.com

INTRODUCTION

Joel Masselink is a geospatial consultant with 12 years of experience in designing maps, curating data, and conducting analyses in support of conservation, development, and environmental projects. Joel uses his diverse geospatial science skillset to solve environmental and sustainability issues.

EDUCATION

Clark University MA, Geographic Information Science

Worcester, MA; 2009

Coursework: geospatial databases, remote sensing, environmental & land change modeling

James Madison University BS, Geographic Science

Harrisonburg, VA; 2005

Coursework: GIS, spatial analysis, spatial statistics, image processing; minor in History.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Earth Logic, LLC Principal Consultant

Seattle, WA; 2014 - present

• Providing custom geospatial solutions for clients in the environmental, natural resources, and international development sectors.

SELECT CONSULTANCIES

- · Great Elephant Census Forest Initiative Data Analysis. Consultancy for Wildlife Conservation Society.
- Spatial Data Assessment of Large-Scale Infrastructure in the Lower Mekong Region. Consultancy with *Wildlife Conservation Society*.
- Standardizing Large Mammal Surveys to the SMART-Ecological Records Data Model for Central Africa. Consultancy with *World Resources Institute*.
- · Cartography of DRC Protected Area network. Consultancy with World Wildlife Fund / PARAP.

Microsoft via Insight Global Geospatial Data Analyst

Bellevue, WA; 2018 - 2019

· Managed releases, evaluated metrics, and performed analytics on new sources for Bing Maps data.

Vulcan, Inc. GIS Developer, Impact Engineering

Seattle, WA; 2015 – 2018

- · Contributed geospatial data processing and visualization to software engineering projects.
- · Provided data quality assurance, management, and mapping for large-scale wildlife surveys.

Wildlife Conservation Society GIS Coordinator

Democratic Republic of Congo; 2009 – 2013

- · Built GIS capacity through training, mentoring, and project management.
- · Managed and analyzed spatial data for land-use planning and wildlife monitoring activities.
- · Conducted land-cover mapping, land-change assessment, and species distribution modeling.

USAID Africa Bureau Intern, CARPE

Democratic Republic of Congo; 2008

· Designed landscape maps for Congo Basin Forest Partnership publication, State of the Forest 2008.

NAEVA Geophysics GIS Specialist / Database Manager

Charlottesville, VA; 2006 – 2007

Managed target databases and provided GIS support for geophysical surveying projects.

Joel A. Masselink

Residing in: Seattle, Washington phone: +1 (774) 232-7629 website: www.joelmasselink.com e-mail: jmasselink@gmail.com

SKILL SUMMARY

· Geoprocessing using GDAL/OGR commands, Python, ArcPy, and ModelBuilder

- · Familiarity with authoritative proprietary, public domain, and open geospatial datasets (OpenStreetMap)
- · Geospatial database management (PostgreSQL/PostGIS, Esri ArcGIS Server, SQL Server, Cosmos)
- · Spatial / geostatistical analysis and image processing techniques (ENVI, Earth Engine)
- · Expert mapmaking skills using desktop platforms (ArcMap, QGIS) and Mapbox Studio
- · Familiarity with collaborative software engineering and version control systems (Git/GitHub, SVN)
- · Experienced GIS software trainer and MissingMaps mapathon facilitator
- · Strong written and oral communication skills, strong leadership capacity

CONTRIBUTOR TO PUBLICATION

International Union for Conservation of Nature Species Survival Commission (IUCN/SSC) Primate Specialist Group & Institut Congolais pour la Conservation de la Nature (ICCN). 2012. Bonobo (Pan paniscus): Conservation Strategy 2012–2022. Gland, Switzerland: p.65

Hickey, J., J. Nackoney, N. Nibbelink, S. Blake, A. Bonyenge, S. Coxe, J. Dupain, M. Emetshu, T. Furuichi, F. Grossman, P. Guislain, J. Hart, C. Hashimoto, B. Ikembelo, O. Ilambu, B. Inogwabini, I. Liengola, A. Lokasola, A. Lushimba, F. Maisels, **J. Masselink**, et al. 2013. Human proximity and habitat fragmentation are key drivers of the rangewide bonobo distribution. Biodiversity and Conservation. Vol. 22, Issue 13, p.3085-3104.

ADVISORY BOARD MEMBERSHIP / VOLUNTEERING

Tusubira-We Have Hope treasurer & board member Seattle, WA; 2014 – present technical support to Ushahidi Seattle, WA; 2017 – 2018 Water supply engineering GIS support Uganda, 2005

PROFESSIONAL ASSOCIATION MEMBERSHIP

- · Global Leadership Forum Cohort XII (2019)
- · Global Washington Ambassador
- · Pangea Giving Circle of Friends
- OpenStreetMap US and OpenStreetMap Foundation member
- · Society for Conservation GIS member

GEOGRAPHIC EXPERIENCE

· United States, Democratic Republic of Congo, Uganda, Philippines

LANGUAGES

- French proficiency
- · Basic Luganda, Spanish, and Swahili